I'd like to start my performance by saying 90 percent of everything is crap.
أود أن أستهل العرض بالقول أن 90 بالمائة من الأشياء محض هراء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's called Sturgeon's law, and what that means
يُدعى قانون (ستورجيون) وهذا يعني
is that the majority of anything is always bad.
أن معظم الأشياء دائماً ما تكون سيئة
I have a giraffe here.
لدي زرافة
I'm going to throw the giraffe behind my back
سأدير ظهري وسأرمي بهذه الزرافة
and whoever catches it is going to help me on this next thing.
فمن يلتقطها سيساعدني فيما سيأتي لاحقاً
Sir, you caught the giraffe.
سيدي، الزرافة بحوزتك
I have a playing card in my hand.
لدي ورقة لعب في يدي
Freely name any card in the deck.
اختر رقماً عشوائياً من ورق اللعب
Audience member: 10 of hearts.
العشرة الكبة
You could have named any card in the deck,
كان من الممكن لك اختيار أي ورقة أخرى
but you said the 10 of hearts.
لكنك اخترت العشرة الكبة بالذات
Ninety percent of everything is crap,
90 بالمائة من الأشياء محض هراء
so there's this to prove that Sturgeon was correct.
وهذا دليل أن (ستورجيون) كان على حق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Sir, this is not your show.
سيدي، هذه ليست محاضرتك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Keep the giraffe for a moment, okay?
احتفظ بالزرافة قليلاً، حسناً؟
Jesus.
رباه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Crazy people.
أناس معتوهون
Well, the truth is,
في الحقيقة
why is the majority of everything bad?
لماذا معظم الأشياء سيئة؟
And my answer is: I think we stop thinking too soon.
وإجابتي هي كالتالي: أعتقد أننا نتوقف عن التفكير بسرعة
I'll give you a clear little example,
سأعطيكم مثالاً بسيطاً
something that people used to do around the turn of the century --
ثمة ما اعتاد الناس القيام به في مطلع القرن
not this century, the other one.
ليس هذا القرن بل القرن الآخر
The idea was to take a piece of paper
الفكرة تتمثل بالتقاط قطعة من الورق
and fold it inside out using only your weaker hand,
وطيّها من الداخل باستخدام يدك الأضعف
in my case, the left hand.
بالنسبة لي اليد اليسرى
Something that would look like this.
سيبدو الأمر كذلك
By the way you reacted, I can see your lack of interest.
بالمناسبة ردة فعلكم توحي بعدم الاهتمام
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But that's okay, I understand why.
لكن لا بأس، أتفهم السبب
We stop thinking too soon.
نتوقف عن التفكير بسرعة
But if we give it a little bit more thought,
وإذا أضفنا فكرة أخرى
like a paper clip.
كمشبك للورق مثلاً
A paper clip makes this a little bit more interesting.
مشبك الورق يضفي قليلاً من المتعة
Not only that, if instead of using my hand with the fingers,
ليس ذلك وحسب، فبدلاً من استخدام يدي وأصابعي
I use my hand closed into a fist,
سأستخدم يدي وأغلقها لتصبح قبضة
that makes this even a little bit more interesting.
مما يضفي قليلاً من المتعة أيضاً
Not only that, but I will impose myself a time limit of one second,
ليس ذلك وحسب، بل سأفرض على نفسي مدة زمنية قدرها ثانية واحدة
something that would look like this.
ليبدو الأمر كذلك
Now -- no, no, no.
الآن.. لا داعي
Sturgeon may be correct.
ربما (ستورجيون) على حق
But he doesn't have to be correct forever.
لكن ليس بالضرورة أن يكون محقاً للأبد
Things can always change.
فالأشياء قد تتغير دائماً
Sir, what was the card?
سيدي، أي ورقة كانت؟
The 10 of hearts?
العشرة الكبة؟
There's this to prove that things can always change --
وهذا دليل على أن الأشياء تتغير دائماً
the 10 of hearts.
العشرة الكبة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Secrets are important.
الأسرار هامة
And secrets are valuable.
والأسرار قيّمة
And this is the best secret I've ever experienced.
وهذا أفضل سر تعلمته
It starts with a deck of cards onto the table,
تبدأ بأوراق اللعب على الطاولة
an old man and a claim,
ورجل مسن ومقولة:
"I will not touch the deck till the end."
"لن ألمس الورق حتى النهاية"
It doesn't matter who the man was,
لا يهم من كان الرجل
all that matters was that sentence ringing in my head:
كل ما يهم أن الجملة كانت تتكرر في رأسي:
"I will not touch the deck till the end."
"لن ألمس الورق حتى النهاية"
Now, during all this time,
طوال تلك المدة
he was holding a small notebook
كان يحمل مفكرة صغيرة
that sometimes he would open and flip through the pages
ويفتحها من وقت لآخر ويقلب في الصفحات
and look at something.
وينظر إلى شيء ما
But I was not really paying attention to the book
لكنني لم أعر المفكرة اهتماماً
because I was paying attention the deck and the claim he had made before,
بل كان انتباهي مركزاً على الورق وعلى الجملة التي قالها سابقاً
"I will not touch the deck till the end."
"لن ألمس الورق حتى النهاية"
Now sir, you have the giraffe.
والآن سيدي، الزرافة بحوزتك
Go ahead, throw it in any direction
حبذا لو ترميها في أي اتجاه
so that you can find someone else at random.
بحيث تذهب لأحد آخر لا على التعيين
Perfect. Sir, you're going to play my role in this story.
رائع. سيدي ستلعب دوري في هذه القصة
The old man turned to me and he said,
استدرك الرجل المسن وقال لي:
"You could pick a red card or a black card."
"اختر إما ورقة حمراء أو سوداء"
My answer was ...
إجابتي كانت...
Audience member 2: The black card.
أحد الحاضرين: البطاقة السوداء
HG: Indeed!
بالفعل!
It was a black card.
كانت ورقة سوداء
He said, "It could be a club or a spade,"
قال: "اختر إما البستوني أو السباتي"
and my answer was ...
وكانت إجابتي...
Audience member 2: Spade.
أحد الحاضرين: السباتي
HG: Indeed! It was a spade.
بالفعل! كانت السباتي
He said, "It could be a high spade or a low spade."
قال: "اختر إما ورقة كبرى أو صغرى"
And my answer was ...
وإجابتي كانت...
Audience member 2: A high spade.
بستوني كبرى
HG: Indeed! It was a high spade.
بالفعل! بستوني كبرى
Since it's a high spade, it could be a nine, a 10,
بما أنها بستوني كبرى فقد تكون تسعة أو عشرة
a jack, king, queen or the ace of spades.
أو الولد أو الملك أو الملكة أو الآص بستوني.
And my answer was ...
وكانت إجابتي...
Audience member 2: The king.
الملك.
HG: The king of spades, indeed.
ملك البستوني، بالفعل.
Now sir, let's be fair.
والآن سيدي، لنوضح الأمور
You selected black, you selected spade,
أنت اخترت الأسود، واخترت البستوني.
you selected the high spade, and you selected -- sorry?
واخترت ورقة كبرى واخترت.. عذراً؟
Audience member 2: King. HG: King of spades.
- الملك. - ملك البستوني.
Did you feel I influenced you in any decision?
هل تظن أنني أثّرت على قرارك؟
Audience member 2: No, I just felt your energy.
لا، شعرتُ بطاقتك وحسب
Because if not, we could start all over again.
وإلا فيمكننا إعادة الكرة من جديد
But it was really fair? Audience member 2: Absolutely.
- لكنك اخترت بملء إرادتك؟ - بالتأكيد
HG: Now, the old man turned to me and he asked me one more question,
والآن استدرك العجوز إلي وطلب مني طلباً آخر
a number between one and 52.
رقماً بين 1 و52
And the first number I thought of was ...
والرقم الأول الذي تبادر إلى ذهني كان...
Audience member 2: 17.
17.
HG: Indeed! It was the 17.
بالفعل! كان الرقم 17
The old man only said one more thing:
أضاف العجوز قائلاً:
"This is the end."
"إنها النهاية"
And I knew exactly what that meant.
وكنت أعلم ماذا يعني ذلك
I knew that he was going to touch the deck.
علمت أنه سيلمس الورق.
Everything that you're about to see is exactly as it looked.
كل ما سترونه الآن هو تماماً كما بدا.
He took the deck out of the box.
أخرج أوراق اللعب من العلبة.
Nothing in the box.
العلبة فارغة.
He counted, "One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, 10."
وأخذ يعد: واحد.. اثنان.. ثلاثة.. أربعة.. خمسة.. ستة.. سبعة.. ثمانية.. تسعة.. عشرة
The tension was building.
كان التوتر يتصاعد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17."
"11.. 12.. 13.. 14.. 15.. 16.. 17.."
And on the 17, instead of the king of spades,
وعند 17، بدلاً من ملك البستوني
something appeared in the middle of the deck,
ثمة شيء ظهر بين أوراق اللعب
that later, I would realize was actually a secret.
واكتشفت لاحقاً أن ذلك الشيء كان سراً.
The old man stood up, he left.
وقف العجوز وغادر
I never saw him again.
لم أره بعدها.
But he left his notebook
لكنه ترك مفكرته
that was there from the beginning.
الذي كان موجوداً هناك من البداية.
And when I picked it up,
وعندما التقطت المفكرة
that was the best secret I've ever experienced.
اكتشفت أنه أفضل سر رأيته في حياتي.
We are defined by the secrets we keep
تتحدد شخصيتنا بالأسرار التي نحتفظ بها
and by the secrets we share.
والأسرار التي نتشاركها.
And this was his way of sharing a secret with me.
وهذه كانت طريقته لمشاركة السر معي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Crazy shit! Now --
ياللجنون! الآن...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I believe that amazing things happen all the time.
أؤمن أن الأشياء المذهلة تحدث دائماً.
I really do.
أؤمن بذلك حقاً.
And the reason why we don't see them as often,
وسبب عدم رؤيتنا لها في أغلب الأوقات
it's because we don't place ourselves in a position
أننا لا نضع أنفسنا في وضعية
to search for those amazing things.
تسمح لنا بالبحث عن هذه الأشياء المذهلة.
But what if we decided to search for those amazing things,
لكن ماذا إذا قررنا أن نبحث عن هذه الأشياء المذهلة
for those small coincidences in life that are truly amazing?
عن تلك المصادفات الصغيرة في الحياة والمذهلة جداً؟
So you have the giraffe,
إذاً الزرافة بحوزتك
go ahead, throw it in any direction so you find one last person at random.
هيا ارمها بأي باتجاه عشوائي بحيث تقع بين يدي شخص آخر من الحاضرين.
Sir, I'm going to ask you,
سأطرح عليك سؤالاً
do you have, with you, a United States $1 bill?
ألديك ورقة دولار أمريكي واحد؟
Audience member 3: I think so.
أعتقد ذلك.
HG: Yes? You see, a coincidence!
نعم؟ أرأيتم المصادفة!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Let's make sure you have it.
لنتأكد أنها بحوزتك
Do you have it?
ألديك ورقة دولار؟
Audience member 3: Yes. HG: Yes! Perfect.
نعم. حسنا! ممتاز.
Now, I want you to do exactly the same thing I am about to do.
والآن، أريدك أن تفعل تماماً كما سأفعل الآن
I have a dollar bill here to explain.
لدي ورقة دولار هنا للشرح.
I want you to take the dollar bill,
أريدك أن تلتقط هذه الورقة
and fold the Washington part inside, like this.
وأن تطوي جزء (واشنطن) إلى الداخل بهذا الشكل.
So you get this kind of big square, okay?
سيتكون لدي مربعاً كبيراً، صحيح
Now, I want you to take the bill and fold it like this, lengthwise,
والآن، أريد أن تطوي ورقة الدولار بالطول بهذا الشكل
so it becomes like a rectangle,
بحيث تصبح أشبه بمستطيل
and then again -- really fold it, really crease it --
ومن ثم مجدداً قم بطيّها جيداً...
and when you have it,
عندما تنتهي من طيها
please fold the bill again into a little square like this
قم بطي ورقة الدولار مجدداً إلى مربع صغير بهذا الشكل
and let me know when you have it.
وأعلمني عندما تنتهي.
Do you have it? Perfect.
هل انتهيت؟ ممتاز
Now, I'm going to approach,
والآن سأقترب منك
and before we start,
وقبل أن نبدأ
I want to make sure that we do this in very, very serious conditions.
أريد أن أحرص على أن نقوم بذلك بشكل جاد للغاية.
First of all, I want to ensure that we have a marker and we have a paper clip.
أولاً، أريد أن أتأكد من أن لدينا قلماً ومشبك ورق.
First of all, take the marker and go ahead and sign the bill.
أولاً التقط القلم وضع إمضاءك على ورقة الدولار.
And this is the reason why:
وإليكم السبب:
later, I'm going to be doing a bunch of stuff on stage
فيما بعد، سأقوم ببعض الأشياء على المسرح
and I don't want you to think,
ولا أريدكم أن تحسبوا
oh, while I was distracted by Helder,
أنني أحاول تشتيت انتباهكم
someone came onstage and swapped the bill.
ليأتي أحد ما إلى المسرح ويبدل الدولار
Now not only that, I want you to take the paper clip
أريد منك أيضاً أن تأخذ المشبك الورقي
and put it around the bill.
وأن تضعه حول الدولار.
So even if nobody comes onstage and switches the bill,
لئلا يستطيع أحد تبديل ورقة الدولار
I don't have enough time to go open the bill and close it
ولكي لا يكون لدي متسع من الوقت لأفتح ورقة الدولار وأغلقها
and see what I don't want to see.
وأرى ما لا أريد أن أراه.
Is that fair?
هل أنتم موافقون؟
Now you can give me the marker back.
يمكنك الآن أن تعيد قلمي لي.
And just like that, very clearly,
كذلك الأمر وبكل وضوح
I want to make sure that we place this in full view
أريد أن أضع ورقة الدولار في مكان مكشوف كلياً
from the beginning of this experience
منذ بداية هذه التجربة
and to make sure that everyone is going to see it,
لكي نحرص على أن الجميع يشاهد ورقة الدولار
we're going to actually have a camera man onstage.
نحتاج لمصور مع كاميرا على المسرح.
Yes, perfect, so that you can see.
نعم، ممتاز، ليتسنى لكم المشاهدة.
That's your signature? Yes? Perfect.
أهذا توقيعك؟ نعم؟ ممتاز
Now, we're going to use also the deck and a glass for this.
سنقوم أيضاً باستخدام ورق اللعب
to search for an amazing coincidence.
للبحث عن مصادفة مذهلة.
Do you mind, can you help me with this?
أتساعدونني من فضلكم؟
Go ahead and take some cards and shuffle.
أريدك أن تخلط هذه الأوراق
And do you mind, can you take some cards and shuffle?
هلا قمت بخلط هذه الأوراق؟
You can take some cards and shuffle.
قم بخلط هذه الأوراق
You can shuffle cards in a variety of ways.
يمكنكم خلط الأوراق بطرق مختلفة
You can shuffle cards like this.
يمكنك خلطها بهذا الشكل
You can shuffle cards in a more messed up way,
يمكنك خلطها بطريقة مبعثرة
something like this.
بهذا الشكل
You can shuffle cards in the American way.
يمكنكم خلطها على الطريقة الأميركية
As a Portuguese, I don't feel entitled to teach you guys how to do it.
بما أنني برتغالي، فلا أظن أنني الشخص المناسب لتعليمكم إياها
But the important part is after shuffling the cards,
لكن الجزء الأهم بعد خلط الأوراق
always remember to cut and complete the cards.
هو أن تقوم دائماً باقتطاع جزء ثم إكمال الأوراق
Do you mind doing that for me, sir?
هلّا تساعدني من فضلك سيدي؟
Please cut and complete.
اقطع وأكمل الأوراق
And when you have it, place the cards up in the air.
وعندما تنتهي، ضع الأوراق للأعلى
And you too, cut and complete and up in the air.
وأنتما أيضاً، ضعا الأوراق للأعلى
Up in the air.
تم خلط أوراق اللعب من قبل واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة، خمسة أشخاص
Now, very clearly, I'm going to gather the deck together.
والآن سأجمع الأوراق.
And just like that.
بهذا الشكل.
I'm going to search for a coincidence in front of everyone.
سأبحث عن مصادفة أمام الجميع.
I'm going to try.
سأحاول.
I have some cards that maybe,
لدي بعض الأوراق التي ربما
maybe they don't mean anything.
قد لا تعني شيئاً.
But maybe that's because we are not paying close attention.
لكن لعل السبب في ذلك أننا لا ننظر إليها عن كثب.
Because maybe, maybe they mean a lot.
فربما تعني الكثير.
Before we start, sir, you gave me a dollar bill.
قبل أن نبدأ سيدي، أعطيتني ورقة دولار.
Is that your signature?
أهذا إمضاؤك؟
Audience member 3: Yes it is.
نعم.
HG: I want you to see very clearly
أريدك أن ترى بوضوح
that I'm going to open your bill
أنني سأفتح الورقة
and reveal a small secret that we created.
وسأكشف سراً بسيطاً قمنا بإنشائه.
And the secret of this dollar bill is the serial number.
وسر ورقة الدولار هذه هو الرقم التسلسلي.
Madam, can you take the dollar bill?
سيدتي، هلا أخذتي ورقة الدولار من فضلك؟
In the serial number, there is a letter.
ثمة حرف في الرقم التسلسلي
What is the first number after the letter?
ما هو الرقم الأول بعد الحرف؟
Audience member 4: Seven.
أحد الحاضرين: سبعة.
HG: Seven.
سبعة
Seven.
سبعة.
But, that's maybe just one coincidence.
لكن، ربما تكون مصادفة بسيطة.
What is the second number? Audience member 4: Nine.
- ما هو الرقم الثاني؟ - أحد الحاضرين: تسعة.
So after the seven, we have a nine.
بعد السبعة، لدينا تسعة.
And after the nine?
وبعد التسعة؟
Audience member 4: Two.
أحد الحاضرين: اثنان.
HG: The two. And after the two?
اثنان، وبعد ذلك؟
Audience member 4: Three.
أحد الحاضرين: ثلاثة.
HG: Three, and after?
ثلاثة، وبعدها؟
HG: Three.
-أحد الحاضرين: ثلاثة. - ثلاثة.
Audience member 4: Seven. HG: Seven.
-أحد الحاضرين: سبعة. - سبعة.
Audience member 4: Four. HG: Four.
-أحد الحاضرين: أربعة. - أربعة.
Audience member 4: Two. HG: Two, and?
-أحد الحاضرين: اثنان. - اثنان، و؟
Audience member 4: Q.
أحد الحاضرين: Q.
HG: Q like in queen?
تقصدين الملكة؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The queen of clubs!
ملكة الأسباتي!
All the cards in order, just for you.
جميع البطاقات في الترتيب، فقط من أجلكم.
And that's my show.
هذه هي محاضرتي.
Thank you very much and have a nice night.
شكراً جزيلاً وطابت ليلتكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)